[SPEAKER_00]: I want to discuss right attention, yoniso, manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha praises this quality many, many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's essential in the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's one of the prerequisites for the right view as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: One out of two.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, because I do not see even a single thing that so-called as unarisen wholesome qualities to arise and arisen unwholesome qualities to decline as right attention for one who attends carefully, unarisen wholesome qualities arise and arisen unwholesome qualities...
[SPEAKER_00]: He just says, one who attends properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, one who attends... Not careful, because people will think all they need to do is be careful and they'll see the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you actually need to know where you're supposed to attend, thus attend it properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rightly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Attend it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are two, these two conditions for arising of right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The utterance of another and proper attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are the two conditions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when he, he, he usually speaks after partition, or depends origination, he uses that proper attention, danger to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I'll just give one example.
[SPEAKER_00]: The last is, this can be found in the connected discourses, Samyutta Nikāla.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, before my enlightenment, while I was still a bodhisattva, not yet fully enlightened, it occurred to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Alas, this world has fallen into trouble, in that it is born, ages and dies.
[SPEAKER_00]: It passes away and is reborn.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet it does not understand the escape from this suffering, headed by aging and death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where now will an escape be discerned from this suffering, headed by aging and death?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, because it occurred to me, when what exists does aging and death come to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what is aging and death determined?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, because, through proper attention, there took place in me a breakthrough by wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is birth, aging and death come to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Aging and death has birth as its determination.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through proper attention, there took place in me a breakthrough by wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as pretty much every other sutta, well, pretty much every sutta, people can either read it kind of superficially, so to speak, and then read that passage as, oh, okay, so the Buddha properly, you know, he was carefully attending, he was really thinking about it, and then he figured it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, it can read like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you actually take every sutta to be a phenomenological description of the nature of experience, nature of things, thus, if understood, a person would be at least a sotāpanna, if not more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in that case, you would approach it quite differently.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if he says...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if he used yoniso manasikāra there, which he did, if he used the same term, that proper attention or the right attention, means proper attention is that which reveals
[SPEAKER_01]: It reveals the principle of dependent origination.
[SPEAKER_01]: The principle that basically has its two factors that are simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it says, with what this condition has this... well, with what this condition is aging and death being manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, you are aging and dying simply by being alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simply by being... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is the simultaneously present condition for that state?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the fact that you are manifested in this human existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what birth is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Birth is not coming out of womb.
[SPEAKER_01]: Birth is manifesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Manifestation of the five aggregates through your appropriation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that starts, when the Buddha said himself, that starts when an embryo is conceived.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already, one is already manifested into this human realm.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what we take to be birth, coming out of womb, in a hospital, is just like one of the
[SPEAKER_01]: But they wouldn't be coming out of womb if there was no embryo conceived in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the birth takes place when the five aggregates manifest, when the five aggregates are bound.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, when the one to be bound is present, and mother and father come together, and mother is in season.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then embryo is conceived.
[SPEAKER_01]: Embryo, that is the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what birth is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that embryo, when it's conceived, simultaneously with its conception, or rather, simultaneously with its manifestation, another thing that manifests simultaneously to that, is aging and death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because growing of the embryo, it's already aging.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already dying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a simultaneous presence of manifestation, aging and death.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is the important thing to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: With dependent origination, it's not the explanation of causality, because every dependent origination description starts with, with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, with, yeah, two aspects.
[SPEAKER_01]: One that determines the other, but both are present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't involve time.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's akālika.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's timeless.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't involve time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that don't involve time are the ones that are, like, in the relationship, are the ones that are simultaneously present to the same extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what proper attention shows you.
[SPEAKER_01]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, if somebody has a right view, all they need to do is practice proper attention, because all they need to do is just bring back to the mind that simultaneous principle of dependent origination.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that will bring all the lust to fade.
[SPEAKER_01]: All aversion to fade.
[SPEAKER_01]: All ignorance to fade.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it says whatever he intends to, he intends rightly, and therefore... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever he intends to, he intends rightly, he intends properly, he intends according to its nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that nature is, it is determined.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll read the... Majjhima Kāyā.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: 2.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the taints.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because this goes into using proper attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Attending to different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the Sābhāsana Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the taints.
[SPEAKER_00]: bhikkhus, I shall teach you a discourse on the restraint of all the taints.
[SPEAKER_00]: Listen and tend closely to what I shall say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, Venerable Sir, the bhikkhus replied.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Vesubhan said this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, I say that the destruction of the taints is for one who knows and sees, not for one who does not know and see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means it's for... at least for the... for the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Who knows and sees what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Proper attention and improper attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: When one attends properly, unarisen taints...
[SPEAKER_00]: When one attends improperly, improperly, improperly, unarisen taints arise and arisen taints increase.
[SPEAKER_00]: When one attends properly, unarisen taints do not arise and arisen taints are abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the taints are three essential desires being in ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there are taints that should be abandoned by seeing, there are taints that should be abandoned by restraining, by using, by enduring, by avoiding, by removing, and by developing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it goes on to each of those.
[SPEAKER_00]: Taints to be abandoned by seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: What taints should be abandoned by seeing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Here Bhikkhu is an untaught ordinary person, who has no regard for noble ones and is unskilled and undisciplined in their dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who has no regard for true men and is unskilled and undisciplined in their dhamma, does not understand what things are fit for attention and what things are unfit for attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Since that is so, he attends to those things unfit for attention, and he does not attend to those things fit for attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are the things unfit for attention that he attends to?
[SPEAKER_00]: They are things such that, when he attends to them, the unarisen taint of sensual desire arises,
[SPEAKER_00]: The taint of being arises, the taint of ignorance arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are the things, unfit for attention, that he attends to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh, it's the opposite when he knows what he's doing, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the the untaught ordinary person also attends in this improper way.
[SPEAKER_00]: He thinks to himself, was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: Was I not in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: Was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: How was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the crucial difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Improper attention is the attention that carries the sense of self, carries the notion of I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Proper attention is the attention that
[SPEAKER_01]: It leaves no room for the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you properly attend, if you say, with this, this is, there is no room for the owner of either this or this, or this or that, or in between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is just no room for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's with the rising of this, this also rises.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather with this, when this is present, this is present too.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, you can take your experience as a whole and you can see that it's utterly, completely determined by the presence of light.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you are alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, whatever you experience is because you're still alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you're experiencing, no matter what
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how it differs particularly, the nature of experience is there, because life is still present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can... you can then just reflect further and say, okay, well, are you in control of that life?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you in control of the beating heart?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you in control of functional brain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you in control of preventing accidents from happening?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, this life that is present,
[SPEAKER_01]: It rests upon the foundations that are utterly inconceivable, inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you fully understand that, then you cannot possibly regard it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what proper attention penetrates.
[SPEAKER_01]: It discerns that there are foundations that undermine you, that you cannot access.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, it restores the right order of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereby, with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: For putrūjana, it's with me, my experience is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am, thus things are for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things are mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's exactly why in that sutra it says, like, somebody who is a putrūjana, uninstructed worldling, who doesn't know how to attend to things properly,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why he ends up wondering these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or was I not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Will I be in the future?
[SPEAKER_01]: How?
[SPEAKER_01]: In what way?
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that revolves around the fact that he completely taken for granted that he is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, now he's just wondering, how is he?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or was he all the time?
[SPEAKER_01]: But he never questions that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even that question of what am I, who am I, when I was, how I was, that already revolves around the present notion of self, present notion of control, which means he's not properly attending to the nature of experience and he doesn't see it as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And seeing it as impermanent means seeing it as not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you have doubts arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, he has all those doubts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, basically, he makes himself liable to that doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, he doesn't recognize that any of those, all of those questions, no matter what the particular thing that they might be asking is, all those questions, in their nature, revolve around the notion of sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already a mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, he'll then just doubt, because none of the answers can be satisfying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Was I?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but was I always?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Will I be?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't know that either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I not now?
[SPEAKER_01]: How am I now?
[SPEAKER_01]: All this, oh, it's just just just permutations of the same same assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he goes beyond doubt to be attenched rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: He goes beyond doubt if he basically
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if he's basically not concerned with those questions, because they're rooted in mistaken assumptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if he attends rightly, he addresses the mistaken assumptions of sense of control, permanence, and I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: By dissolving that, everything that was depending upon it, namely those questions, cannot remain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he doesn't answer the questions, so the sotāpanna, basically, makes them cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: His understanding makes all the questions cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: He goes beyond the doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, after that, a well-taught noble disciple, who has regard for noble ones and is skilled and disciplined in their dhamma, who has regard for true men and is skilled and disciplined in their dhamma, understands what things are fit for attention and what things are unfit for attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Since that is so, he does not attend to those things unfit for attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he attends to those things fit for attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is the way he attends.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: He attends properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the origin of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the way leading to the cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he attends properly in this way, three fetters are abandoning him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Personality view, doubt, and adherence to rules and observances.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are called the tenets of śrīmad-bhāgavatam.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is interesting because he's saying he's a noble disciple who attends in this way, properly, the Four Noble Truths, but then, when he does this,
[SPEAKER_00]: He reaches the fruit of sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because there was the... yeah, there's... in that other sutta, there is a distinction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before a person becomes sotāpanna, he gets attained to the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, dhammanu sāri, sādhanu sāri.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's not sotāpanna yet, but his view is basically now along the right lines.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means he knows what the proper attention is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as that very passage says, when he practices it, he comes to understand this suffering, this is the origin, this is the cessation, this is the way that leads to God.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that... Like, those are four things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, four normal truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're basically all revolving around the same insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Insight into freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, fully understanding all the aspects of that,
[SPEAKER_01]: Can be put into four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand what it makes it be.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand what it makes it not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you understand the way that leads out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, you can connect that to what we just said before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Appropriating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your own life, your own body, your own experience, regarding it as yours, that makes you liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't necessarily suffer on the immediate level, like even if there is nothing unpleasant bothering you, the fact that you have appropriated these things means there is always a looming possibility of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that in itself is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what he recognizes.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the sense of self, I am, cannot stand on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: It always needs, and actually, it's founded upon a foundation, a relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's founded upon a relationship with the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that relationship is, for me, mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you recognize then, that your sense of self depends upon the world, and when I say the world, I mean experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, your sights, your sounds, smell, taste, touches, things that you're experiencing, that's what your sense of self depends on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you then start reflecting and seeing, attempting to properly see, these things that you see, hear, taste, touch, are fundamentally out of your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might exercise degree of the volition once a thing has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even that volition is within much greater image of non-control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as I said, your heart can stop any second.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't even conceive having a say in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, your whole life
[SPEAKER_01]: All the things you experienced, all the things that you will experience, all the things you're experiencing right now, depends upon that beating muscle in your chest that pumps blood.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's as random as this stream around us that kind of runs over these rocks and moves the leaves and branches or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's this movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can also see as a memory.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can't remember that putting your heart together, putting your body together.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, becoming that body, or... you know, as you just had it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it was just given to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was just given to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have no say in its assembly, you have no say in its operating, and you certainly have no say in its ending.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you regard it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that is the discrepancy at the most fundamental existential level.
[SPEAKER_01]: You undo that discrepancy, means you're attending things properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means your attention does not maintain that mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does not maintain that discrepancy, which is a wrong attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's attention of everybody.
[SPEAKER_01]: That patujana attends and every attention maintains that wrong order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Me first, my experience second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance being censored.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are the result of that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by seeing that you can't even own these things, even if you want to, no matter how hard you want to, you recognize, oh, thinking that I own them, or rather, entertaining the notions of ownership, well, that's what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you recognize, this is suffering,
[SPEAKER_01]: The arising of suffering is this very notion of ownership in regard to things that cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, consequently, the cessation of suffering is not the cessation of things that cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, the Buddha did not have to kill himself in order to understand the nature of life.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: While you are alive, you understand the cessation of life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cessation of life is cessation of appropriation of life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he understands that cessation of suffering is removing of appropriation in regard to your life, your existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Removing the ownership, disowning it, not attaining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, how you fulfill that, that's the four noble truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is the path that leads to this fulfillment, to this cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it's basically the the everything that revolves around the right view, and right attention, and right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means that through right view, right attention and right mindfulness, constant practice, it will eventually saturate your whole life, regardless of the circumstances, regardless of the feelings that have arisen, regardless of the pleasant, unpleasant, agreeable, disagreeable perception, regardless of everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right view, right intention, right mindfulness has been brought to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_01]: There will not be any kind of rekindling, so to speak, of the wrong order, of that mistaken notion of ownership, of that habit, basically, of ownership, of that discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's when Noble Eightfold Path has been practiced to its fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there are no traces of that discrepancy left, of those wrong notions left, in any regard.
[SPEAKER_01]: In regard to any sense, or any thought, or any memory, or any future plan.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all saturated with the right attention, with the right mindfulness, with the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, obviously, means right effort, right livelihood, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right concentration.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right composure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right composure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a better translation, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: He goes on to say about the taints to be abandoned by restraining.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here Bhikkhu reflecting wisely, abides with the eye, faculty restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: While taint's vexation fever might arise in one who abides with the higher faculty unrestrained, there are no taints of vexational fever in one who abides with the higher faculty restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, likewise with all the other senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite simple.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's straightforward, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, once the right view is established, that won't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, none of that will work for somebody who doesn't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the sutta opens up, it's the one for the one who sees, one who knows and one who sees.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once the right view has established, then the one with the right view recognizes, okay, now it's about guarding the senses, practicing the restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, none of the mistaken notions, the habits of mistaken notions and discrepancies that are spread or maintained through lost aversion and delusion, none of those will be arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're practicing restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stick to there long enough, and then this... they just... it becomes impossible for them to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like... like... basically having a habit, and then doing... kind of getting rid of the habit.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to stick to the opposite behavior, or to the restraint of the habit, for a certain amount of time, depending of how those have... how strong those habits were.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you stick to it, and practice restraint and so on, and those habits stop arising, that's it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the Noble Disciple writes proper attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: It tends to be abandoned by using.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, Bhikkhu, reflecting properly, uses the robe only for protection from cold, and protection from heat, and contact with flies, mosquitoes, wind, and the sun, and creeping things, and only for the purpose of concealing the private parts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reflecting properly, he uses alms food, neither for amusement, nor for intoxication, nor for the sake of physical beauty and attractiveness, but only for the endurance and continuance of this body, for ending discomfort and for the assisting of the holy life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Considering thus, I shall terminate old feelings without arousing new feelings, and I shall be healthy and blameless and shall live in comfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean by not arousing new feelings?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, like the feeling of hunger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leaking too much?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, so you eat until the old feeling disappears, of hunger, but you don't overeat, so then you have a new feeling of discomfort of being overeaten.
[SPEAKER_00]: He uses the resting places, dwellings, only for protection from cold, from heat, for protection from contact with flies, mosquitoes, wind, sun, and creeping things, and only for the purpose of warding off the perils of climate and for enjoying retreat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reflecting properly, he uses the medicinal requisites only for protection from arisen afflicting feelings and for the benefit of good health.
[SPEAKER_00]: While taints, vexation and fever might arise in one who does not use the requisites, thus, there are no taints, vexation or fever in one who uses them, thus, these are called the taints that should be abandoned by using.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, most of the time, in monasteries, that's what you try to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You try to use those requisites as a monk, like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a... before you have proper attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's something to aspire, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, if you want that to result in the abandoning of the taints,
[SPEAKER_01]: The right view is necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: The right view comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: We've said that many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: It needs to come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't know what you're supposed to do, how can you do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As simple as that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't know what a dhamma is, how can you practice it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It pertains to be abandoned by enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here a bhikkhu, acting properly, bears cold and heat, hunger and thirst, and contact with flies, mosquitoes, wind and sun, creeping things.
[SPEAKER_00]: He endures ill-spoken, unwelcomed words, and arisen bodily feelings that are painful, sharp, piercing, disagreeable, distressing, and menacing to life.
[SPEAKER_00]: While taints, vexation, and fever might arise in one who does not induce things, there are no taints, vexation, or fever in one who endures them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how does he endure, he endures the weather, uncomfortable, uncomfortable feelings, painful experiences?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: By becoming, you know, a lot of people can endure these things, can sort of... Again, again... go to the army.
[SPEAKER_01]: He will not, yeah, exactly, but it will not result in destruction of lust, aversion and delusion, if there is no right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the right view, and with the hardship,
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything that was dependent, any of those habits, any of those discrepancies, they were kind of hiding about, dependent upon cherishing the notions of comfort, for example, will be destroyed with the right view that puts one through discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, discomfort founded upon the right view will destroy any of the things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean that the things were missing there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, in case there were, they would be destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, that's why the Buddha sometimes, like, for some monks, with the right view, ascetic practice, uh, dūtangas, uh, would be resulting in, uh, in, uh, in arahantship, in developing further wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: For some other monks, with the right view, it wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he said, let those who want
[SPEAKER_01]: To exert themselves in such practices, exert themselves in such practices.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, either way, the right view needs to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because, you know, people's habits have evolved differently, people's lusts have proliferated differently.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, the existential discrepancy is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the particular manifestations of it, yeah, that needs to be addressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's basically like, like, you know, you might not necessarily target one by one, but you put yourself out through some discomfort in case things are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically like taking antibiotics to wipe the harmful bacteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't aim at one or two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, just you take a generic one and, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be covered, if you do it long enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will address it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why that sutta, all the tense, means basically, if you go through all of those ways of penetrating, there is absolutely nothing for anyone in the world with the right view, that will be left.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, there are things that you will be destroying by seeing, but then, yeah, for somebody, that might be all.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might be, it might be enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: However, most likely, there will be some other things hiding elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, basically, by going through all of those, through restraint, through enduring, through hardship, through seeing,
[SPEAKER_01]: There will remain nothing uncovered.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, like, like, like antibiotics, let's get back to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some are good for respiratory infections.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you know, some bacterias are resistant to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might not necessarily have those bacterias.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, okay, if you become an arahant by taking only one or two,
[SPEAKER_01]: By practicing only one or two forms of the destruction of taints, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you become completely healthy by taking one or two antibiotics, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you know that you've taken one or two sufficiently enough, but you're still not fully healthy, okay, so there are issues elsewhere, then you try a different antibiotics.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, somebody who gains the right view, reviews their mind and, okay,
[SPEAKER_01]: I got the right view, but I'm not an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means there are things to be done, to be dealt with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's when you start dealing with restraint, guarding the sense faculties.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, yes, sensuality might not be arising anymore, but I still don't feel that I have reached the unsurpassed security for bondage.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, push yourself, take yourself out into this conflict.
[SPEAKER_01]: Endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Avoid.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yes, eventually, you covered all the bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the arhantship will have to be the result.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, what you said, avoiding.
[SPEAKER_00]: The next one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, why is the avoiding?
[SPEAKER_00]: He avoids wild elephants.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he recognizes that he's not an arhant yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, he needs more time to apply himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it would be very foolish to stand in front of the wild elephant,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, quite likely, it will result in his death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with the wild dog, charcoal... no, not charcoal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cesspits.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cesspit, cesspit, not... yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cliffs and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cliffs.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that can kill you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unsuitable seats, wandering in unsuitable places.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that can compromise you, things that can kill you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bad friends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that can distract you from the goal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here Bhikkhu, reflecting properly, does not tolerate an arisen thought of sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: He abandons it, he removes it, does away with it, and annihilates it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And a thought of ill-will, a thought of cruelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: He does not tolerate arisen evil unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: He abandons them, removes them, does away with them, and annihilates them.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you think that means?
[SPEAKER_00]: Seclusion, dispassion and cessation?
[SPEAKER_00]: Each mindfulness factor is supported by seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, seclusion from our wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It results in dispassion, because you're not attracted to things anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cessation of lust, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And relinquishment, freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, it ripens in relinquishment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, those... that becomes built...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And a bhikkhu who dwells restrained with the strength of all the taints, he has severed craving, flung off the fetters, and with the complete penetration of conceit, he has made an end of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what the Blessed One said.
[SPEAKER_00]: The bhikkhus were satisfied and delighted in the Blessed One's words.